# 大家好 現在十天半個月都在下水
Hi everyone! The rain has been pouring for ten days or a fortnight recently.
# 現在都發大水了 這邊都一大片
And it's now flooding. The whole area here,
# 被淹掉了
is now underwater.
# 看一下有沒有魚
Let's see if there are any fish.
# 你看那裡 那個就是我們烤雞的地方
Have a look! There's where we roasted the pheasant.
# 幸好把那個爐子搬回來啦 要不然
Fortunately, we have taken the oven back. Otherwise,
# 爐子都不知道沖哪裡去啦
only God knows where it would be washed to.
# 再去看一下 看一下有沒有魚
Let's have a look again, and see if there are any fish,
# 有沒有魚抓 抓兩條上來
see if we can catch any, and catch a couple of them.
# 發那麼大的水
It's flooding so fiercely.
# 這下面肯定很多魚的
There must be a lot of fish down there.
# 抓不到啊
But I can't catch them.
# 我去看一下那個李子有沒有熟 兄弟家的李子 有幾個
I'm gonna see if the plums over there are ripe. These are my buddy's plums. There are a couple of them.
# 上次蓋了那個葉子的
I covered it with a leaf last time.
# 應該熟啦
I think they should be ripe now.
# 你看
Look!
# 上次我蓋了蓋子的
I gave it a cover last time.
# 就這個
It's this one.
# 它現在 不是很熟
It's now, not too ripe.
# 有點紅了 看到沒有
It's a bit red, see?
# 好脆呀
It's so crunchy!
# 還沒沒沒 不是很熟
It's still, still, still, not too ripe.
# 就還一一個
Just one here
# 這裡還有一個哦
Here's another one.
# 你看 這個都 都開裂啦
Look! This has already, already cracked open.
# 一半開裂 一般[SIC]沒開裂
Half has cracked open, but not the other half.
# 我吃這半沒開裂的
I'll have the other half.
# 這個好吃
It's tasty.
# 嗯
Um!
# 這個李子我們這邊叫 豬血李
We call this type of plums "pig blood plums" here.
# 跟那三華李不一樣的哦 你看
They're not the same as the Sanhua plums, look!
# 這個脆肉
This is crunchy.
# 三華李是軟肉
But Sanhua plums are soft.
# 這裡有一個
Here's another one.
# 爆掉啦 真的是
It's cracked. What a pity!
# 看一下還有沒有
Let me see if there are any more.
# 一個也是愛呀
Even just one is a sign of love.
# 一個都沒了
Not even one
# 看一下其它樹上 這棵樹上還有沒有
Let's see if there are any more in other trees, in this tree.
# 樹就那麼多
There are so many trees though.
# 你看 這個是我們以前經常烤東西的地方哦
Look! This is where we used to come grilling.
# 現在都被水沖啦
It's now flooded.
# 江乾淨一點 下次再來烤
Let the flood cleanse the place. We'll come grilling again next time.
# 今天早上水還更大 現在還好
The flood this morning was even more fierce. It's not too bad now.
# 退了一點 不然更大嘞
The flood has gone away a bit. Otherwise it would be much more fierce.
# 我回去拿幾個地籠來 放一下地籠
Let me go back and get some traps. I'm gonna put some traps here.
# 看能不能抓到一些魚
Let's see if we can catch some fish.
# 那麼大的水應該有魚
The flood is so fierce. There must be some big fish.
# 你看這個板栗
Have a look at the chestnuts here!
# 今年肯定很多板栗的
There must be a lot of chestnuts this year.
# 那麼小的樹就長那麼多板栗
There are so many chestnuts in such a small tree.
# 一樹都是哦
All over the tree
# 秋天就是收獲的季節
Autumn will be the harvesting season.
# 以後我們就來摘
We can come and pick them later.
# 把這個刀磿一下
I'm now sharpening the knife.
# 剛沒那個 沒有誘餌哦
I've just run out of, you know, run out of baits.
# 蚯蚓現在下雨又挖不到
And it's not possible to catch any earthworms in rainy days.
# 剛好上面有鴨子 把那個鴨子 割點它的肉來 做誘餌
It just so happens that there are ducks up there. Let me cut off some meat, from a duck, to be my bait.
# 吃肉的 吃肉的魚 它會進那個 就會騙進地籠裡面去
The carnivorous, carnivorous fish, are gonna, I mean, will be deceived into the traps.
# 把它抓起來
Then I can catch them.
# 黃鱔啊 蛇頭魚呀 鯰魚呀
The eels, the snakehead fish, the catfish,
# 還有那些小魚呀 它們都會進去吃
and also the small fish, they'll be going into the traps,
# 吃鴨肉的
for the duck meat.
# 等下我去抓個鴨子上來
I'm gonna catch a duck.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個鴨子 現在越來越瘦
This duck, is now getting skinny day by day.
# 鴨肉我吃膩啦 我換點魚肉來 一樣的其實
I'm already tired of duck. So now I exchange it for some fish. They're the same, actually.
# 這個鴨肉砍好(註︰沒有原字幕)
The duck has now been chopped up.
# 取了那麼一點點 剩下的
I just take a tiny little bit here. The rest,
# 我自己吃
is for me.
# 拿個袋子來裝起來
Let me put them into a bag.
# 這個鴨子 一半都去了
The duck, half of it is gone.
# 這裡還有2個地籠 一直都在這裡
Here are two more traps. They've always been here.
# 刀也帶過去
I'll take the knife as well.
# 這個水都漲了一半多 那麼深啦
The water here is raised by a half. It's so deep now.
# 等下我要 脫鞋子下去才行啦
I'll need to, I have to take off my shoes.
# 這裡還有
Here as well
# 放點肉 放點肉下去
Put some meat, put some meat into the trap.
# 它們才會進來玩
Then they'll have fun in the trap.
# 不放點肉下去它們不進來
They won't be coming in if there isn't any meat.
# 夠了
Enough
# 綁住這個
Tie it here.
# 我們去上面 上面放地籠
Let's go up there, put some traps up there.
# 上面還有個地方
There are more place up there.
# 褲子都濕啦 沒事 等下回去就洗澡
My pants have got wet. No worries. I'm gonna take a shower when I get back.
# 你看 就是那個水潭
Look! It's the pond over there.
# 那水潭肯定很多蛇頭魚的
There must be a lot of snakehead fish in that pond.
# 你看 這裡搞的 搞的像 像 像個雨林一樣
Look! It has become, become something like, like, like a rain forest here.
# 這個最大的
This is the largest one,
# 最大的 給它丟中間
the largest one. Put it right in the middle.
# 這一個 一個就放滿啦
Just one. One already fills up the pond.
# 這裡 這裡也放一個
Here, let me put one here as well.
# 這裡那麼深
The water is so deep here.
# 哎 夠啦 大塊吃肉啊
Ay! Enough! Have a big piece of meat!
# 這一塊給它 大塊肉給你們吃
Leave them this piece. I'm gonna give you guys big pieces of meat.
# 可以 肉
Alright! No more,
# 沒啦
meat.
# 這一個放在這裡
I'm gonna put this one here.
# 等下搞了個大貨 大魚 跑了怎麼辦嘞
It would be too bad if I have a big one, a big fish and it runs away.
# 明天 明天再過來看
Tomorrow, let's come again tomorrow.
# 看明天 肯定有魚的
Let's see. There must be fish tomorrow.
# 現在發了大水 魚都喜歡出來玩
When it floods, the fish will come out to have fun.
# 出來玩它就看到這個食物
When they come out to have fun, they'll see the food.
# 看到這個食物它就很想吃
When they see the food, they'll crave for it.
# 很想吃它就進來籠子
And when they crave for it, they'll get into the traps.
# 剛剛好
Perfect!
# 第二天
The next day
# 你看 今天天晴啦 我去收一下地籠
Look! It's sunny today. We're gonna get back the traps.
# 借了兄弟的這個 這個 這個水 水衣
I've borrowed the, this is, this water, water jacket from the buddy.
# 全副武裝
Full gear!
# 誒呀 好像看到螃蟹啦
Eya! I seem to see some crabs.
# 你看 螃蟹
Look! Crabs,
# 好幾個螃蟹哦
a couple of crabs.
# 你看 好多這個螃蟹 看看一二三四
Look! A lot of this kind of crabs. See? One, two, three, four.
# 等會我帶回去
Let me take them back.
# 這個有沒有
Are there any here?
# 全是小魚
All are small fish,
# 沒有大魚
no big fish
# 難搞哦 這個
It's, no good.
# 你看
Look!
# 螃蟹 小魚 好多
A lot of crabs, small fish...
# 看一下 最後一副網
Let's see, how the last trap is doing.
# 沒有
Nothing
# 我們把這個帶回去 這個一條魚都沒有的 這裡
Let's take it back. Here's, here's not even one fish.
# 嗯 這些魚不喜歡吃鴨肉 是不是
Um! I bet that these fish don't like duck meat at all, right?
# 就幾條泥鰍
Just a few loaches
# 虧大了
Too bad!
# 你看 一隻鴨子搞下去
Look! I've invested one whole duck,
# 一條魚都沒搞到
but I have not even one fish in return.
# 這個有點大哦
This one is a bit too big.
# 哇 這個魚就蠻多的 你看
Wa! Here are quite a lot of fish, look!
# 有一條
Here's a,
# 有一條鯰魚 還有螃蟹
a catfish, and some crabs.
# 看一下 還有一個籠子
Let's have a look! There's still one more trap.
# 哎呀 有魚有魚
Aya! Fish, fish!
# 額 有一條蛇頭魚
Eh! Here's a snakehead fish,
# 還有一個鯰魚
and also a catfish.
# 這個可以呦
It's not bad!
# 搞了三條
So we have three fish,
# 三條大的
three big fish.
# 把這個 收一下
Let me, pack them up.
# 你看 我用這個來裝 裝這個魚
Look! I'm gonna put, put the fish into this pot.
# 這 有魚
Yea, fish here.
# 蛇頭魚
Snakehead fish
# 這條夠大 這個
This is really big, this one.
# 還有小魚嘞
And also some small fish
# 有螃蟹
Some crabs here
# 搞的肉都搞了
The meat, I've taken,
# 搞了兩斤 魚就搞了那麼一點點
I've taken a kilogram of meat, only to have just a tiny little bit of fish here.
# 把這個網曬一下
I'm gonna dry the traps under the sun.
# 一天打魚
One day fishing,
# 三天都在曬網
then three days drying the traps
# 曬乾
Dry them,
# 下次我們繼續
and let's go again next time.
# 你看 這幾條就養著
Look! I'll keep these couple of fish here.
# 像這樣的蛇頭魚我就把它養著
I'm gonna keep these snakehead fish.
# 這個也是
And this one too
# 誒 不聽話啊 這條
Ey! It's naughty, this fish.
# 來 到這裡來
C'mon! Come here!
# 還有一條
One more
# 這些小魚 全部用來 把它全部煎掉它去
These small fish, are all... I'm gonna fry them all.
# 這些魚很好吃的呦
These fish are really tasty.
# 味道還是很OK的
The taste is quite okay.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.